Guide to the Katharine Buell Wilder Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Additions since 1987, 1764-1996
  - December 1994 Acquisition, 1898–1992; 12.63 linear feet (16 boxes)
    - Bernard Heinz's Writings and Research
      - "Auto Chapter" handwritten on loose notebook paper, undated (Box 22, Folder 383)
      - "Music Chapter" handwritten on loose notebook paper, undated (Box 22, Folder 384)
      - Theodore Winthrop and Frederic Church research materials
        - Typescript of Theodore Winthrop article and copy of article published in The New Haven Register, 1978 September 24; undated (Box 22, Folder 385)
        - "Frederic Edwin Church: The Icebergs" by Gerald L. Carr with enclosed letter from Robert V. Rozelle, Director of Public Relations at the Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, 1980–1981 (Box 22, Folder 386)
        - "Waiting", copy of poem written by Winthrop in 1851, undated (Box 22, Folder 387)
        - Copied correspondence from the University of Texas, Austin, undated (Box 22, Folder 388)
        - Copy of The Daily Palladium with death announcement and Heinz's book proposal, 1980; undated (Box 22, Folder 389)
        - Book proposal on Frederic Church and his social circle, undated (Box 23, Folder 390)
        - Correspondence with Winslow Ames, 1977–1985 (Box 23, Folder 391)
        - Writings on White Mountain, poems of Theodore Winthrop, Rose Terry Cooke and Frederic Church, copies, 1977; undated (Box 23, Folder 392)
        - Research including call slips, notes and article copies, undated (Box 23, Folder 393)
        - George William Curtis notes and copied correspondence, undated (Box 23, Folder 394)
        - "The Life and Poems of Theodore Winthrop" edited by his sister, copy (2 folders), undated (Box 23, Folder 395-396)
        - Notes and outline on Winthrop, undated (Box 23, Folder 397)
        - Winthrop article photocopies, undated (Box 23, Folder 398)
        - Civil War reports excerpts, undated (Box 23, Folder 399)
        - Typescript drafts of Heinz's New Haven Register article about Winthrop, 1978; undated (Box 23, Folder 400)
        - Correpondence photocopies from the University of Virginia and the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 401)
        - Notes labeled by years of Winthrop's life from 1848 to 1859, undated (Box 23, Folder 402)
        - "TW Milestones" written by Bernard Heinz, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 403)
        - "A Companion to The Heart of the Andes" written by Theodore Winthrop, photocopy, undated (Box 23, Folder 404)
        - Library inquiries on Winthrop research, 1977–1985 (Box 23, Folder 405)
        - Photocopied photographs of Winthrop, photographs of Winslow Ames and correspodence with Elaine Evans Dee of the Cooper- Hewitt Museum, 1935–1978 (Box 23, Folder 406)
        - Photographs of Winthrop, his spurs, and a sketch owned by Winslow Ames, 1958 (Box 24, Folder 407)
        - Olana clippings, correspondence, brochures, slides, and photographs (2 folders), 1965–1988 (Box 24, Folder 408-409)
        - Frederic E. Church's "The Icebergs" and Sotheby Catalog featuring American 19th and 20th century paintings, drawings, watercolors, and sculpture, 1979–1980 (Box 24, Folder 410)
        - Winthrop family notes, undated (Box 24, Folder 411)
        - William Winthrop notes, correspondence, and photocopied letters, 1977–1990 (Box 24, Folder 412)
        - Church photocopied correspondence, articles, clippings, and notes, 1977–1980 (Box 24, Folder 413)
        - Correspondence about William Worthington's paintings, inventory of paintings in Othneil C. Marsh's house, 1974–1975 (Box 24, Folder 414)
        - Frederick Osborn and Frederic E. Church's correspondence copies, Frederick Osborn and Bernard Heinz correspondence, 1979–1985 (Box 24, Folder 415)
        - Louis Remy Mignot, photocopied biographical entry, undated (Box 24, Folder 416)
        - Isaac Israel Hayes photocopied articles, correspondence about his papers, notes, 1979–1982 (Box 24, Folder 417)
        - "A Portfolio: The Artist and the Civil War", National Historical Society article, undated (Box 24, Folder 418)
        - "Old Yale: Brief and prolific- the life and death of Theodore Winthrop, 1848", Yale Alumni Magazine, 1985 February (Box 24, Folder 419)
        - Copies of "Theodore Winthrop- Civil War Hero and Secret Author", The New Haven Register, 1978 (Box 25 (oversize), Folder 420)
        - Photocopied Theodore Winthrop correspondence, 1977 (Box 25 (oversize), Folder 420 a)
      - Photocopied correspondence addressed to "Constable", undated (Box 26, Folder 421)
      - Gold Selleck Silliman photocopied correspondence, undated (Box 26, Folder 422)
      - William Thornton and Thomas Jefferson photocopied correspondence, undated (Box 26, Folder 423)
      - Matthew Carey and Thomas Jefferson photocopied correspondence, undated (Box 26, Folder 424)
      - Matthew Carey and William Livingston photocopied correspondence, undated (Box 26, Folder 425)
      - Yale College library notice reproduction, undated (Box 26, Folder 426)
      - Direct Marketing mailers and pamphlets, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 427)
      - "Paul and Fran take home and office along to raise funds", Fund Raising Magazine, original magazine, 1971 July; 1974 September 5 (Box 26, Folder 428)
      - Proposal and correspondence concerning bringing the Universalist Historical Society's library to the Harvard Divinity School (2 folders), 1979–1980 (Box 26, Folder 429- 429a)
      - "The Mechanics of Book Manufacturing" and "The Forbes Senate Bid- An Estimate; Political Spotlight Stolen from Hess" Raritan Valley News, undated (Box 26, Folder 430)
      - Here's How Bazaar catalog, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 431)
      - Meadville/Lombard Theological School fundraising files, 1971 (Box 26, Folder 432)
      - Direct marketing mailing information and Unitarian Universalist District of Metropolitan New York Annual Reports, 1971–1972 (Box 26, Folder 433)
      - Consumer Defense Volunteer Office correspondence, clippings, and photograph, 1942 (Box 26, Folder 434)
      - Addition to Stamford Advocate article- resume, undated (Box 26, Folder 435)
    - Family Papers
      Included in the photograph files of this series are tintypes, daguerrotypes, and photographs. Also included is a very rare tintype of an exterior shot of a man and a woman sitting in a carriage outside a house in Folder 464.
      - Photographs
        - Julia Klauber Samter, Jeanne Heinz, Katharine Loving Buell Wilder, and Jeanne Samter Heinz photographs, 1953; undated (Box 28 (oversize), Folder 450)
        - Bernard Heinz photographs from childhood to adulthood, undated (Box 28 (oversize), Folder 451)
        - Photographs at Deer Lake, 1910–1969 (Box 28 (oversize), Folder 452)
        - Northfield School and High School photographs, 1933–1937 (Box 28 (oversize), Folder 453)
        - Waldorf Astoria photograph, 1921 (Box 28 (oversize), Folder 453 a)
        - Bernard Heinz photograph album, 1916–1919 (Box 29, Folder 454)
        - Bernard Heinz photographs from childhood to adulthood, 1919–1945 (Box 29, Folder 455)
        - Photographs from rented manor and dock, 1937–1938 (Box 29, Folder 456)
        - Samter family photographs, 1896–1922 (Box 29, Folder 457)
          Includes the following photographs: Julia Klauber Samter and Liste Klauber, 1938 (?); Samuel Samter and Julia Klauber Samter, undated; Samuel Samter and two unidentified males, 1922; Samuel Samter, 1922; Samuel Samter last studio portrait, 1851- 1928.
        - Samter family photographs, 1916–1938 (Box 29, Folder 458)
          Includes the following photographs: Jeanne Samter Heinz and Bernard Heinz in passport photographs, summer 1935; Jeanne Samter Heinz and Bernard Heinz Jr., undated; Bernard Heinz Jr. at Ellis Oppenheimer; Bernard Heinz and Jeanne Samter Heinz, 1928; Maurice Heinz in his study Fulton Street, Allentown, Pennsylvania; Bernard Heinz Sr., Jeanne Samter Heinz; Bernard Heinz Jr. passport photograph, 1927; Bernard Heinz Sr. and Jeanne Samter Heinz on 25th wedding anniversary trip to Bermuda, July 1938; Bernard Heinz Jr and Jeanne Samter Heinz, January 1916; Jeanne Samter Heinz and Bernard Heinz Jr., undated; Andover, circa 1931; Bernard Heinz Sr. and Geraldine Miller Jeanne Samter Heinz, wedding photograph of Jeanne Samter Heinz, 1932.
        - Levy family photographs, undated (Box 29, Folder 459)
        - House photographs, 1945; undated (Box 29, Folder 460)
        - Photograph of Bernard Heinz Jr. in nursery with dog, 1913–1914 (Box 29, Folder 461)
        - Buell family photographs, undated (Box 29, Folder 462)
        - Daguerreotype of possibly the Dodge Buell family of Cleveland, undated (Box 29, Folder 463)
        - Buell Dodge family photographs, 1910–1939 (Box 29, Folder 464)
          Very rare tintype of man and woman in a carriage outside a house.
        - Heinz family photographs, 1899–1930 (Box 29, Folder 465)
        - Cased daguerreotype photographs
          - Unidentified man, undated (Box 29, Folder 466)
          - Two unidentified boys, undated (Box 29, Folder 467)
          - George Dodge, son of G.C. Dodge, brother of Anna Buell Dodge, undated (Box 30, Folder 468)
          - Unidentified family, undated (Box 30, Folder 469)
          - G.C. Dodge. One photograph of Mrs. George Dodge is also included., undated (Box 30, Folder 470)
          - Three unidentified young men, undated (Box 30, Folder 471)
          - Unidentified woman, undated (Box 30, Folder 472)
      - Family tree, undated (Box 31 (broadside))
      - Scrapbook inscribed to Jeanne from Aunt Eliza, 1898 (Box 32 (oversize), Folder 473)
      - "The Name and Family of Buel(l)", genealogical and historical sketch from the Media Research Bureau, Washington D.C., undated (Box 33, Folder 474)
      - Dr. Eramus Darwin Burton papers, 1914 (Box 33, Folder 475)
        Photograph of Uncle Eramus's house on Euclid Avenue in Cleveland, Ohio. He was a physician and known to the family as "Uncle Darwin" Undated paper written by Dr. E. D. Burton for the Centennial of the First Presbyterian Church of East Cleveland; memorial program for Dr. Eramus Darwin Burton, 1825- 1914
      - Handwritten and typescript accounts of grandparents, author unknown, undated (Box 33, Folder 476)
      - Hasper family handwritten accounts, undated (Box 33, Folder 477)
      - Copies of Rosa Abeles' childhood stories and correspondence from Rosa and Joseph Abeles to Bernard and Susanna Heinz, 1985–1992 (Box 33, Folder 478)
      - Maurice Heinz's obituary clipping and copy, 1945 (Box 33, Folder 479)
      - Prom Magazine and photocopied article "Former cadet saves AF Academy $150,000" from The Flyer, 1964–1976 (Box 33, Folder 480)
    - Bernard Heinz Personal Papers
      - S.S. Leviathan materials, 1927 (Box 33, Folder 481)
      - Bayard Taylor Breezes and stamp collection charter, 1927–1928 (Box 33, Folder 482)
      - Sherwood and Robin Hood programs and newspaper clippings, 1928–1929 (Box 33, Folder 483)
      - Sundown Lariat anthology, 1930 (Box 33, Folder 484)
      - Andover Exeter, 1930–1932 (Box 33, Folder 485)
      - Poems written by Heinz and his friends, and University of Pennsylvania Commencement program, 1937; undated (Box 33, Folder 486)
      - Defense of the West class notes, 1941 (Box 33, Folder 487)
      - Poetry class notes, 1942 (Box 33, Folder 488)
      - Army files, 1941–1943 (Box 34, Folder 489)
      - The New Yorker and The Scranton Times clipping, 1941–1946 (Box 34, Folder 490)
      - Kiskiminetan (the Kiski School yearbook), 1944 (Box 34, Folder 491)
      - Raritan Valley News, 1950 November 16 (Box 34, Folder 492)
      - The Metropolitan Opera program for Salome, 1964–1965 (Box 34, Folder 493)
      - The New York Times articles on the Moon landing, 1969 June (Box 34, Folder 494)
      - Newspaper clippings of Richard Nixon and the Moon landing articles, 1969–1974 (Box 35 (oversize), Folder 495)
      - Diplomas from the University of Pennsylvania and Harvard, 1937-1940 (Box 35 (oversize), Folder 496)
      - Pages from scrapbook including newspaper clippings and music, 1938–1946 (Box 35 (oversize), Folder 497)
      - Scrapbook, 1945–1947 (Box 35 (oversize), Folder 498)
      - Scrapbook, mostly of "Uncle Henry's History Book" and one letter, 1945–1947 (Box 35 (oversize), Folder 499)
  - June 2002 Acquisition, 1888–1993; 3.99 linear feet (7 boxes)
    The June 2002 Acquisition is arranged in loose groupings as received by the library.
    The June 2002 Acquisition includes Bernard Heinz's personal and professional writings and research. It also includes his and Susanna Wilder Heinz's personal papers and family photographs.
    - Bernard Heinz's Writings and Research
      - "The Music Box Secret" typescript outline, undated (Box 36, Folder 500)
      - "Searching for Aaron" files
        - Typescript outline, undated (Box 36, Folder 501)
        - Typescript of Chapters 1-9 and fragments of other chapters, undated (Box 36, Folder 502)
        - Typescript of Chapters 10- 20, undated (Box 36, Folder 503)
        - Typescript of Chapters 21- 26, undated (Box 36, Folder 504)
        - Typescript of Chapters 1- 16, undated (Box 36, Folder 505)
        - Typescript of Chapters 16- 26, undated (Box 36, Folder 506)
        - "First finished" typescript copy pages 1- 125, undated (Box 37, Folder 507)
        - "First finished" typescript copy pages 126- 199, undated (Box 37, Folder 508)
        - "First finished" typescript copy pages 200- 349, undated (Box 37, Folder 509)
        - Correspondence with literary agents about manuscript publication, 1973–1993 (Box 37, Folder 510)
      - Connecticut Tercentenary Program of Events, Places of Historical Interest program, and related materials, 1935–1982 (Box 37, Folder 511)
      - "Managing Employees in the Aircraft Industry" and "Some Observation on the NAF Inspector's School", 1942–1943 (Box 37, Folder 512)
      - Providence, Rhode Island brochures and correspondence (2 folders), 1975–1981 (Box 37, Folder 513-514)
      - Miscellaneous manuscripts and writings, undated (Box 37, Folder 515)
        This file includes short writings by Heinz including "The Crash", "The Girl from County Mayo", "The Civics Lesson", "Teasing", "The Fan", "The Letter", fragments from "Senior Citizen Card"; correspondence with literary agents, and family members; clippings copies.
      - Garvan Furniture at Yale clippings, brochures, and correspondence, 1960–1977 (Box 38, Folder 516)
      - Bernard Heinz's untitled papers written for classes, undated (Box 38, Folder 517)
      - Notes and an essay written on Louis Phillippe, undated (Box 38, Folder 518)
      - Walt Whitman notes, William Dean Howell's "Drum-Taps" and letter from Petra L- (Box 38, Folder 519)
      - Bound essay on Caroline of Ansbach, undated (Box 38, Folder 520)
      - Bound essay entitled "The Madrid Embassy of Sir Benjamin Keene, 1749- 1757", 1940 (Box 38, Folder 521)
      - "Center Church on-the-Green" pamphlet, undated (Box 38, Folder 522)
      - Correspondence with literary agents and publishers about the publication of magazine articles, 1973–1993 (Box 38, Folder 523)
      - Stamford, Connecticut Unitarian Universalist Church related materials
        - Stamford church notes, correspondence with Polly Mewhard, and P.T. Barnum's "Why I am a Universalist", 1971 (Box 38, Folder 524)
        - Stamford church notes and correspondence, 1971–1977 (Box 38, Folder 525)
        - Spiritualism notes and clippings, 1972–1979 (Box 38, Folder 526)
        - Spiritualism correspondence, clippings, and photographs, 1972-1980 (Box 39, Folder 527)
        - "1870 Meets 1971" script at the Unitarian Universalist Society in Stamford, additional sermons, and correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 39, Folder 528)
        - History of Universalism discussion outline, "Why I am a Universalist" by P.T. Barnum copy, and 1971 correspondence with Mrs. Alvin C. Bruel (Box 39, Folder 529)
        - Dr. J. Smith clippings and notes, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 530)
        - Copies of handwritten documents and newspaper articles on the Universalist church in Stamford, CT, undated (Box 39, Folder 531)
      - Miscellaneous articles, clippings and correspondence, 1978–1988 (Box 39, Folder 532)
    - Family Papers
      - Framed hairwork, gift from Rosa Klauber to her daughter Julie, 1897 November 26 (Box 40 (oversize))
        Inscription on the back of the hairwork is written in German and Yiddish.
      - Harper's Weekly ads, 1899 (Box 41 (oversize), Folder 533)
      - Cartoons pasted to the back of Life calendar (Box 41 (oversize), Folder 534)
      - Katharine Buell Wilder's typescript autobiography, 1949 March (Box 42, Folder 535)
      - Photographs
        - "Lonesome Hurst", Hinsdale; Brattleboro, Vermont, and the 1888 blizzard (Box 42, Folder 536)
        - Klauber family, undated (Box 42, Folder 537)
        - Framed photograph of an unidentified woman, undated (Box 42, Folder 538)
        - Framed photograph of unidentified woman, undated (Box 42, Folder 539)
      - H. Wilder's pencil sketches, undated (Box 42, Folder 540)
      - Life Magazines, 1906–1910 (Box 42, Folder 541)
      - Certified copy of last will and testament of Julia Samter, 1960 (Box 42, Folder 542)
    - Bernard and Susanna Heinz Personal Papers
      - Susanna Wilder Heinz and Bernard Heinz's correspondence with local history librarian in Stamford, CT, 1972–1996 (Box 42, Folder 543)
      - Correspondence with Rabbi Julian Miller and souvenir postcards of Wilkes-Barre, PA, 1922–1988 (Box 42, Folder 544)
      - Marriage certificate of Bernard Heinz and Jeanne Samter; Christmas letter from Susanna and Bernard Heinz, 1913–1975 (Box 42, Folder 545)
      - Pamphlets
        - "Chinese Festivals", 1941 (Box 42, Folder 546)
        - "Pocket Guide to India", 1942 (Box 42, Folder 547)
        - "Pocket Guide to Burma", 1943 (Box 42, Folder 548)
        - "Kuan Yin: The Legends of the Eight Immortals", 1944 (Box 42, Folder 549)
        - "Pocket Guide to China", 1944 (Box 42, Folder 550)
        - "Chinese Religious Beliefs", 1944 (Box 42, Folder 551)
        - "Chinese Symbolism", 1945 (Box 42, Folder 552)
  - December 2015 Acquisition, 1764–1996; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
    The December 2015 Acqusition is arranged in loose groupings as received by the library.
    The December 2015 Acquisition contains Susanna Wilder Heinz's personal papers, photographs, and writings. The series includes correspondence documenting her speaking engagements at Unitarian Universalist churches, her work on a book about her cat and cat ownership, and her relationships with her family members.
    - Susanna Wilder Heinz Personal Papers
      - Susanna Wilder school files, 1932–1942 (Box 43, Folder 553)
        Diplomas and report cards
      - Report cards and commencement program, 1931–1942 (Box 43, Folder 554)
      - Framed photograph of girl and boy in a plane, with inscription "lady editor and aviator Simmons", undated (Box 43, Folder 555)
      - Bernard Heinz death annoucements, death certificate, eulogy, 1993–1994 (Box 43, Folder 556)
      - Photographs and writings, 1933–1952 (Box 43, Folder 557)
        Photograph of Susanna Wilder, January 1947; photograph of "me, Eleanor Sery Felber, Jones Beach, August 1947"; photograph of Susanna Wilder at Church of All Souls, 80th and Lexington, New York City, 1952; photograph of Sweet Briar, 1948 taken by John Potter; photograph of Ward- Belmont in Nashville, Tennessee; poem entitled "Shadow Hour" to Susanna Wilder from John Phelps, 1933; school paper written by Susanna Wilder "The Disinherited Knight", undated.
      - Typed letter to unknown recipient from Susanna Wilder describing her education and career; and negative photograph, undated (Box 43, Folder 558)
      - Northfield related photographs and clipping, 1937; undated (Box 43, Folder 559)
        Susanna Wilder hair age 6; various photographs of houses, people and flooded areas labeled "Wilder"; clippings from Greenfield Recorder- Gazette dated Friday May 14, 1937 "Girl, Boy Lead Graduation Exercises at Northfield"; and two photographs of groups of students.
      - Photographs, 1938–1944 (Box 43, Folder 560)
        Susanna Wilder and her friends, various school group pictures, and pictures from a wedding in which Susanna Wilder was a bridesmaid.
      - Correspondence, 1994–1996 (Box 43, Folder 561)
        Both professional and personal correspodence mainly focused on Susanna Wilder Heinz's speaking engagements and writings.
      - Unitarian Universalist worship files, 1980 (Box 43, Folder 562)
        Sermon copies, programs from conferences, and copies of worship hymns.
      - Handwritten chart of Christian denominations and Methodist family tree, undated (Box 43, Folder 563)
      - Sheffield sermons and readings, 1971 (Box 43, Folder 564)
      - Henry Whitney Bellows biography typescript manuscript, undated (Box 43, Folder 565)
      - Unitarian Universalist speaking engagements and correspondence (3 folders), 1962–1988 (Box 44, Folder 566-568)
      - Notes, clippings, and sermons on religious education, 1965; undated (Box 44, Folder 569)
      - Religious programming files, 1958–1960 (Box 44, Folder 570)
      - Bible study notes and correspondence, 1961 (Box 44, Folder 571)
      - Typescript notes on St. Joshua, undated (Box 44, Folder 572)
      - Cat manuscript drafts, undated
        - "My Friend- the Cat" typescript manuscript, undated (Box 44, Folder 573)
        - "The Tilt of his Tail or Talking with Throckmorton" typescript manuscript, undated (Box 44, Folder 574)
        - "The Tilt of his Tail" publishers' correspondence, 1965–1969 (Box 44, Folder 575)
        - Throckmorton typescript manuscript, undated (Box 44, Folder 576)
    - Family papers
      - Holman family records, 1920; undated (Box 44, Folder 577)
        Last will and testament of Janice A. Wilder, undated; letter to Robert Holman Wilder from his mother dated February 13, 1920 about the enclosed Holman family history.
      - George Crogham notes and bibligraphical essay, 1974; undated (Box 44, Folder 578)
      - Dodge Buell information, 1968–1976 (Box 44, Folder 579)
        Photocopied family history; clipping from The New York Times, August 3, 1968 with obituary of Henry Dodge; correspondence between Bernard Heinz and Henry Levien, 1975- 1976; obituary clipping of Lucy B. Buell, undated
      - Loving family papers, 1876; undated (Box 44, Folder 580)
        Christmas 1876 letter to Delia from her brother John; "Dear Father's hair died June 23, 1871" and "Dear Mother's hair died April 12, 1867"; article photocopies, personal histories, photocopied letters, and handwritten genealogies.
      - Kneeland family papers, 1973–1991 (Box 44, Folder 581)
        Susanna Wilder's great-great grandparents were Joseph and Polly Kneeland. This folder includes correspondence between Bernard Heinz and members of Chesterfield Historical Society concerning the Kneelands; photocopies of articles on Samuel Kneeland, Timothy and Maria (Stone) Kneeland, descendants of John Kneeland, the Colonial Period and the Furniture of the Lower Connecticut Valley
      - Bernard Heinz's correspondence about the Wilder family, 1973–1975 (Box 45, Folder 582)
      - Holman and Wilder family papers, 1764–1973 (Box 45, Folder 583)
        Correspondence about Kneeland house in Chesterfield and articles, 1973; photocopies of Christmas carols and church manual; handwritten family tree, undated; 1913 Pension notice for Frederick B. Holman; application for admission to Soldier's Home in New Hampshire filed by Frederick B. Holman, January 7, 1920; Holman family record, circa 1860; Holman family notes; family list written on the back of a Ederheimer Skin and Co. clothing advertisement dated April 8, 1905; Wilder family records of births, marriages and deaths.